<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Live with Sass</title>
    <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com" />
    <updated>2023-10-20T15:58:23-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.livewithsass.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Write the Docs Portland 2022 talk recording</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/write-the-docs-2022-beating-the-virginia-blues.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/write-the-docs-2022-beating-the-virginia-blues.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/10/Beating-the-Virginia-Blues.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="presentationswithsass"/>

        <updated>2023-10-20T15:58:23-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/10/Beating-the-Virginia-Blues.png" alt="Screenshot of a slide displaying Beating the Virginia Blues: Thru-hiking strategies to help you survive your next big project" />
                    Beating the Virginia Blues: Thru-hiking strategies to help you survive your next big project In 2018, I quit my job to hike the entire Appalachian Trail, also known as the AT. It took me 163 days. That’s 163 days of carrying everything I owned on&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/10/Beating-the-Virginia-Blues.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Screenshot of a slide displaying Beating the Virginia Blues: Thru-hiking strategies to help you survive your next big project" /></p>
                <div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/oqp0joQmazE?si=sJ3vWs-8FlLutVH5" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></div>
<p><span style="color: var(--headings-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.42383em; font-weight: var(--font-weight-bold); letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">Beating the Virginia Blues: Thru-hiking strategies to help you survive your next big project</span></p>
<div class="talk-content">
<div class="talk-description">
<p>In 2018, I quit my job to hike the entire Appalachian Trail, also known as the AT. It took me 163 days. That’s 163 days of carrying everything I owned on my back, hiking for 10-12 hours a day, wearing the same clothes every day, and eating lots of foods in bar or dehydrated form.</p>
<p>The AT covers roughly 2100 miles as it crosses 14 states, from Georgia to Maine; Virginia is the single longest state, about a quarter of the trail. It has the reputation for causing a lot of potential thru-hikers to quit--so much so that the state of mind is known as the "Virginia Blues."</p>
<p>Virginia was the roughest state for me, by far. But using a variety of strategies, I was able to stay on trail and successfully complete my thru-hike.</p>
<p>Our work lives are full of large endurance projects. They can be really exciting, like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Starting a new knowledge base from scratch</li>
<li>Taking ownership of an existing set of documentation</li>
<li>Building new curricula or programming</li>
<li>Building a major new feature</li>
<li>Hiking a really long trail (okay, maybe not this one)</li>
</ul>
<p>In all of these projects, there's an initial phase of enthusiasm and excitement followed by a period of productive work. Then there's this period in the middle where things feel all wrong--we don't feel like we're making progress; the project feels like it will never end; we feel overwhelmed; and it might even feel totally hopeless or outright impossible.</p>
<p>Somehow, we power through and finish the project. But we don't talk a lot about that rough patch in the middle. Until now.</p>
<p>This talk is all about that rough patch in the middle. You'll walk away with some actionable strategies you can use to help survive this lull in your next big project. And a few random facts about the Appalachian Trail to wow your friends.</p>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Am I not a maker?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/am-i-not-a-maker.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/am-i-not-a-maker.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/9/record-stand-edited.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2023-10-20T15:38:30-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/9/record-stand-edited.webp" alt="Photo of Kate&#x27;s record player stand, which includes two shelves for records. The record player sits on the top" />
                    I've been spending a lot of time lately thinking and reflecting on who I am, what I'm doing, and what I'm going to do next. Think of it as a taking stock period before making changes, if you will. And one of the things I'm&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/9/record-stand-edited.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Photo of Kate&#x27;s record player stand, which includes two shelves for records. The record player sits on the top" /></p>
                <p>I've been spending a lot of time lately thinking and reflecting on who I am, what I'm doing, and what I'm going to do next. Think of it as a taking stock period before making changes, if you will.</p>
<p>And one of the things I'm working on is embracing the idea of being a maker.</p>
<p>Or, to be more specific, on battling some sense of imposter syndrome or unworthiness of the maker title.</p>
<p>I am a person who makes things. I create written content here and elsewhere, for starters. I also design and build my own furniture. It's nothing fancy, but it is functional and has clean lines. I usually find some kind of design online to use as a starting place or inspiration, and then create my own thing custom-tailored to the space and function I have available.</p>
<p>I don't have a garage or workshop space, and I don't even own a table saw, so it's quite an ordeal trying to do work on our tiny outside deck when it's not raining, or working up clamps and fences to rip plywood using a circular saw. My lack of a great space or tools likely does impact the quality of what I produce, but I'm still really happy with the stuff I build.</p>
<p>In the past year, I designed and built a storage shelf/display area for my turntable and LPs, as well as a couch with two chaises. In previous years, I built my own bed frame and one for a friend, my own spice rack and one for a friend, DVD shelves for my partner, and my bedside tables.</p>
<p>And I've recently started experimenting with making artistic spore prints of mushrooms, to extend one of my hobbies into a thing I can make, too.</p>
<p>So why, one might ask, haven't I historically identified as a maker? And why am I shifting into using the label at all?</p>
<p>Good questions, my lovely. Let's take them one at a time.</p>
<h2>Why I haven't considered myself a maker</h2>
<p>What feels like a lifetime ago, in my early twenties, I definitely described myself as a writer. I pursued two degrees in writing and a lot of my life was consumed by working on essays, short stories, and poems.</p>
<p>After I graduated with my M.A., I started adjunct teaching. And slowly, perhaps inexorably, I got so bogged down in the day-to-day of grading papers and preparing lessons and all the rest, I stopped my own writing. I focused on helping my students improve theirs, instead.</p>
<p>When I got burnt out on writing, I stumbled my way into the tech industry, by way of teaching myself how to design and administer databases. (For those of you fellow database geeks, I figured out third normal form organically and without knowing that's what it was called--relational database architecture just made sense to me.)</p>
<p>Somewhere in there was when I stopped thinking of myself as a writer, because I wasn't writing anymore and it felt odd to call myself that.</p>
<p>And despite the fact that I was designing and building databases, I never considered these creative or maker-worthy tasks.</p>
<p>As my tech career evolved, I started working at a small software company. I worked very closely with software engineers/developers, and that's basically what I've been doing for the last nine years. I've scoped features, done manual testing, written documentation, led webinars and training sessions on things. I've worked closely with devs to make decisions about how best to structure a feature or tweak a user interface.</p>
<p>But during that time, I always considered what I did as enabling and supporting people who did the "real" work of building the thing. I didn't write code or build features; I just did all the rest of the background work to make that possible.</p>
<p>Friends and coworkers would build their own websites from scratch, and I always felt somehow less creative or maker-ish because I preferred to use tools or frameworks that did most of the lifting for me.</p>
<p>At my most recent role, we tried to implement <a href="https://www.eosworldwide.com/what-is-eos" title="What is EOS? Overview of the Entrepreneurial Operating System" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Entrepreneurial Operating System (EOS)</a>. The EOS model depends on a sort of split between a visionary (usually a CEO) and an implementer (usually a COO). It was clear, in every second of those discussions, that I was viewed as an implementer. My job wasn't to dream or come up with ideas; my job was to actually make the ideas a reality.</p>
<p>Many of those changes came down when I was at my heaviest Long Covid-induced brain fog, and to be fair, I <em>wasn't</em> generating a lot of ideas at that time. It was all I could do just to get through the day and not forget important events, concepts, or what I had started doing fifteen minutes ago.</p>
<p>Though we ultimately ended up not sticking with EOS, that binary division--and being on the implementer side of it--stuck with me. And it stuck with me long after my Long Covid baseline improved. I started writing this blog, for example. I started working out designs and measurements and building furniture again (which, I must say, is definitely a bit more complicated when you feel like your math skills aren't great anymore and you quadruple-check your math and still sometimes get things wrong!).</p>
<p>And yet, I still didn't think of myself as being especially creative or a maker.</p>
<p>So what changed?</p>
<h2>A tipping point</h2>
<p>There are few times in my life when I can point to a single crystalline moment where it felt like things changed, but in this case, I can.</p>
<p>I was having a text conversation with a dear friend, who I'm just going to call D here. At one point, I started talking to her about feeling angsty and like I was "over" software, but that I had no clue what to do instead.</p>
<p>And she, being the amazing human that she is, asked me some questions about what I enjoyed doing. Then she took it one step further and started dropping prompts into ChatGPT of all things, to get it to suggest ideas and business plans to move forward.</p>
<p>And many of those prompts had to do with very "maker" things: writing, building furniture, building frames for spore prints and selling them, giving talks on my experiences, etc.</p>
<p>It might sound silly, but that conversation helped me see myself a bit the way I imagine most of the people who know me DO see me: as a creative person.</p>
<p>Whether that's creative problem-solving, or writing a talk or blog post, or baking bread, or designing and making things myself, it occurred to me that a lot of the ways I choose to spend my time <em>are</em> creative pursuits, and they are pursuits that involve me making things, in some form or another.</p>
<p>I don't have to be a web developer to claim that title. I don't have to sell what I do. And I certainly don't have to be the world's most professional furniture builder to do it.</p>
<h2>Why call it a maker at all?</h2>
<p>I certainly don't have to have a label to do these things; so why add the label at all?</p>
<p>Oh, my lovely, I wish this had an easy answer. I'd love to say that I have transcended labels and I don't need them anymore. But the truth is, there's power in calling a thing by its name.</p>
<p>So much of processing the grief around a chronic illness is processing all the identities it makes you lose. I can't really consider myself an endurance athlete anymore, for example: my body just won't do it. I can't be the hustle and grind gal who travels a ton, either: my body just won't do it. The topology of my day-to-day and month-to-month existence is wildly different.</p>
<p>Those labels aren't really important, but the sense of self that was underneath them, and losing that, does.</p>
<p>So many of my posts here are about that grief, or figuring out what it means, and trying to reclaim my sense of self as a result. (See, for example, literally every blog post on here, though especially: <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/on-resiliency.html" title="On resiliency" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">On resiliency: Why I ditched the "you'll get better" narrative</a> or <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/third-times-the-charm.html" title="Third time's the charm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Third time's the charm: Sass loses taste and smell yet again</a> or <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/a-novel-ecosystem.html" title="A novel ecosystem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A novel ecosystem</a> or <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/on-brain-fog.html" title="On brain fog" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">On brain fog: I never had to dream a paper moon</a>, for starters.)</p>
<p>But a huge part of processing that grief is to find new identities or routines or narratives to push you forward. I don't want to be sitting here constantly lamenting what's gone. I also need to find some good--some hope--in the life I'm living. Living, not just surviving.</p>
<p>Using the label might also be an act of defiance.</p>
<p>I defy that Long Covid has destroyed my ability to create things, or to tell meaningful stories. I defy this shitty reality we're all living in that seems to try to strip us of all things joyful. I defy the business and tech worlds that seem bent on painting people like me as implementers rather than creatives.</p>
<h2>But...what is a maker?</h2>
<p>Make: has a very short, lovely piece called "<a href="https://makezine.com/article/maker-news/what-is-a-maker-you-are/" title="What Is A Maker? You Are | Make:" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What Is A Maker? You Are</a>". It includes a quotation and a video clip from Adam Savage that resonates with me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans do two things that make us unique from all other animals; we use tools and we tell stories. And when you make something, you’re doing both at once.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's true that code isn't a tool I'm comfortable with. It's also true that my brain is not as sharp or fast as it was pre-Covid.</p>
<p>But neither of those things means I'm not a maker. I use tools. I tell stories. Sometimes I use tools to help me tell stories.</p>
<p>Maybe it's a silly act of defiance to slap a label on that. My homemade couch isn't going to change the world. Not on its own, anyway.</p>
<p class="dropcap">But if my homemade couch makes me feel creative, autonomous, energized--and if it's also a thing of comfort for my partner and the few people I allow inside my home--then it IS revolutionary.</p>
<p>It's revolutionary because it's helping me to defy a system of work that tells me I'm just a cog in a machine. Cogs don't think, they don't dream, they certainly don't make things. They're just workers, replaceable bits.</p>
<p>It's revolutionary because it's helping me to defy a system of consumption that reduces my entire existence down to my purchasing power, that implies that the only avenues I have to change the world are choosing what I buy.</p>
<p>I'm not a machine. I'm not a cog. And I sure as shit am not just a consumer.</p>
<p>I'm a human. Perfectly imperfect, struggling to figure myself out. Very human, one might say.</p>
<p>And because I'm a human, I'm also a maker.</p>
<p>As you are, my lovely. As we all are.</p>
<p>We don't have to make things for profit to be makers. We can just make.</p>
<p>We don't have to make things that will go viral or that will prompt people to pay us as influencers. We can just make.</p>
<p>For the sheer joy and sense of satisfaction in making something. Anything.</p>
<p>Use your tools. Tell your story. And tell me about it!</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On brain fog: I never had to dream a paper moon</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/on-brain-fog.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/on-brain-fog.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/8/IMG_20180817_075351.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2023-04-07T15:22:22-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/8/IMG_20180817_075351.jpg" alt="A photo of Flagstaff Lake in Maine, taken from the rocky shore. Most of the lake is covered in fog." />
                    I've been trying to figure out how to talk about one of those more elusive long Covid symptoms: brain fog. This is one of those symptoms that seems to be easy for non-longhaulers to dismiss. It's therefore one of the things I wish I could&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/8/IMG_20180817_075351.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A photo of Flagstaff Lake in Maine, taken from the rocky shore. Most of the lake is covered in fog." /></p>
                <p>I've been trying to figure out how to talk about one of those more elusive long Covid symptoms: brain fog.</p>
<p>This is one of those symptoms that seems to be easy for non-longhaulers to dismiss. It's therefore one of the things I wish I could explain well.</p>
<p>So back when I was in my early twenties, I was getting a Master's in Writing. I wrote all kinds of things, though I preferred poetry and short fiction. At least three separate times over the course of about a year and a half, I tried to write a poem about Ella Fitzgerald. It never came out right.</p>
<p>Then I studied poetry with Allison Adelle Hedge Coke. Allison pushed me and my writing in ways I hadn't been before, shoving me outside of the comfort zone of the more narrative/intellectual poems I'd been writing and into something a bit more freeform.</p>
<p>Of course I resisted that. I think every student has to, for a while.</p>
<p>But then one day partway through the semester, I suddenly got a first line about Ella Fitzgerald. And when I wrote it down, an entire poem came tumbling out. A poem totally unlike anything else I had ever written. It leaped through parts of my life, half-forgotten things, made some bold statements, and in so many ways felt like a fitting ode to scat and jazz.</p>
<p>I really can't stress how much of a break from my "usual" work this was. For me, it was more visceral, less linear, pulling together seemingly totally disparate threads from my own life. In many ways, it didn't feel like it came from me, but from somewhere else, like I was just a conduit for something the universe wanted to say.</p>
<p>I took it to class full of energy, and while not all of it made sense to my classmates, I got generally positive feedback on it. I made a few tweaks.</p>
<p>And when I went to perform it at our monthly community open mic, I tried something I had never done with any of my other poems: I memorized it and performed it from memory, no scrap of paper or notes in sight.</p>
<p>That process of memorizing each line prompted some small wording tweaks because there were just ways that the words fit together in my memory that were different from what I had on the page. I can still remember standing in my grad assistant office with its cream cinder block walls, reciting it over and over again aloud after everyone else had gone home for the day, making small adjustments, laughing at myself when I kept forgetting the same lines.</p>
<p>From that moment on, the poem became a part of me. I recited it at that open mic, and again from my memory when I gave my public thesis reading.</p>
<p>But for me, it transcended literary gatherings. I would recite it to myself when I was sad or depressed or angry. Similar to how some people use the Lord's Prayer, I think--it was a series of words that grounded me, calmed me, reminded me there was a much bigger world than my present moment and that I was connected to that world. I would often recite it while I was out hiking, because something about it felt so joyfully present.</p>
<p>But I often used it in the most stressful moments:</p>
<ul>
<li>Almost a decade later, I was traveling in Europe and ended up touring Dachau on my thirtieth birthday. I was getting a different degree this time, on a school trip, but I had a hard time getting back on the tour bus. I wanted to cry and rage and scream; I didn't understand how inhuman and inhumane humans can be. (I still don't understand this.) I sat in a row of bus seats by myself and quietly whispered this poem to myself, through tears.</li>
<li>A year later, in the midst of my divorce, I took endless walks to calm my mind, and I got into meditation. I would recite the poem repeatedly on walks, and I often said it when I settled down to meditate, as a way to clear my mind and set an open intention.</li>
<li>My mom died the day before I started my move from Washington, DC, to Maine. And on the first day of the move, so many things went wrong. I'd scheduled movers to help me load up my moving truck and reserved my building's loading dock, but when I picked up the truck and got to the dock, a utility vehicle blocked the dock. My movers were there, already on the clock, and I had to track down a front desk worker who could track down the electrician to get him to move his car, which delayed everything by almost 45 minutes. Then once everything was packed and loaded, I went back to the moving truck location to have them hook up the trailer for my car and get my car loaded, and none of the staff there seemed to know how to hook the car up. In the end, instead of leaving DC around 1pm, I left at the start of evening rush hour. I then had to drive through a Noreaster (because of course I did), and almost got blown off the Delaware Memorial Bridge. I kept reciting the poem aloud, trying to stay awake and together enough to get through the drive.</li>
<li>And when I was thru-hiking and my mind had exhausted every other thing it could think of to occupy itself, I would often recite it to myself or aloud as I hiked, timing the rhythm of the words to my footsteps.</li>
</ul>
<p>Which is to say: I could call upon this poem at any moment, often under extreme emotional or physical duress, and it was always there. I could feel the shape of the stanzas, I knew all the pauses, I long ago stopped having to think about the words and just had them come tumbling out.</p>
<p>So, fast forward a bit, to a random Friday night in November 2022. I was, by this point, a good two and a half years into long Covid. I felt I was managing really well--my fatigue wasn't totally debilitating, I'd figured out how to manage my energy better so I mostly wasn't having huge flares in symptoms, and most people I interacted with had no idea that I'd been through anything so hard.</p>
<p>I was driving home from buying groceries on a day that had felt somewhat stressful, and as had been happening a lot, my mind circled the stress of still not being able to buy a house. A lot of my stress in 2021, 2022, and 2023 has been from this--my landlord has raised our rent and periodically threatens to sell our house; I want to buy a house so I have stability, a yard for my dog, a garden for myself, and to have some control over expensive things like furnaces and hot water heaters.</p>
<p>For whatever reason, driving home this night, I was near tears.</p>
<p>And to calm myself, I started stuttering out the poem. It's an ancient comfort now, nearly 20 years old.</p>
<p>And I couldn't make it through the end of the first stanza.</p>
<p>It just wasn't there, in my head, anymore.</p>
<p>The whole comforting shape and feel of the poem, of words that I had thought permanently etched into my psyche...it was gone.</p>
<p>I tried to save it, to skip the end of the first stanza, to jump into a place I could remember further down, which helped me re-remember part of the first stanza, but then I forgot the next stanza's transition and the entire ending.</p>
<p>But "forgot" isn't the right word. I didn't forget it. There was just nothing where it normally was, a gaping hole that I was flailing around in, trying to find something to hold onto.</p>
<p>It was as if someone had slapped me, or dropped me into a pool of ice. The shock--and the horror--of it being gone...it's the creative thing I'm the proudest of having written, and it had become a kind of mantra through thick and thin, a kind of prayer against the dark and the horror. A thing that was so much a part of me that I could remember it in extreme stress, and yet here I was, on a fairly normal Friday night, and I was clutching at tiny fragments of it instead.</p>
<p>I did fully start crying at that point. Somehow I didn't drive off the road. Somehow.</p>
<p>As a long-ago graduation present, two dear friends printed a lovely version of my poem as a small poster, with a photo of Ella Fitzgerald. I framed it and it hangs in my entryway.</p>
<p>When I got home, I reread it.</p>
<p>The words were there, and that was some comfort, but the <em>feel</em> of the poem's shape was gone. I could recognize the words as things I'd written, and parts of them conjured feelings for me, but that deeply ingrained feeling that had been a part of me since I had first memorized it...that was gone.</p>
<p>I don't know if anyone who's not inside my head can understand how brutal this loss was. But this is exactly what long Covid brain fog is. It takes things you know inside and out, extremely well...and then it hides them, makes them feel foreign and unfamiliar when you least expect it.</p>
<p>Today, writing this, I just closed my eyes and recited the poem, albeit somewhat haltingly. Most of it is here, now. But I don't trust it. It feels like I am forgetting something important, like I should go check the text to be sure.</p>
<p>This is what this illness does to you. Even when you are doing "well", it's a tenuous and fragile wellness, and it takes so little to make you doubt that perceived wellness.</p>
<p>So please, if you are an otherwise healthy person, please don't think that forgetting to do a task at work, or forgetting to buy eggs when you're at the store, is comparable to the brain fog those of us with chronic illnesses have. If you haven't felt like a core memory or piece of you has gone missing on a dark and miserable night and might never find its way home, then it's not brain fog.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A novel ecosystem</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/a-novel-ecosystem.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/a-novel-ecosystem.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/7/PXL_20221227_203016050.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2023-01-27T12:21:08-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/7/PXL_20221227_203016050.jpg" alt="A large white-green lichen, ruffled in shape, lying on a bed of pine needles with a few twigs sticking out" />
                    For months now, I know I've been past the point of considering long Covid as something I'll "get over". I still know some longhaulers who aggressively follow the research (both real and bullshit) and keep trying to find that one magic answer that will "fix"&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/7/PXL_20221227_203016050.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A large white-green lichen, ruffled in shape, lying on a bed of pine needles with a few twigs sticking out" /></p>
                <p>For months now, I know I've been past the point of considering long Covid as something I'll "get over". I still know some longhaulers who aggressively follow the research (both real and bullshit) and keep trying to find that one magic answer that will "fix" them. I'm not one of those people. At this point I've read enough about chronic illness to recognize that what I have falls into that class of illness, and the shift has been to one of managing it rather than trying to fully recover from it.</p>
<p>And when I've tried to describe this attitude to people, what I usually say is something like this:</p>
<p>Collectively, we tend to view the body in mechanical terms. Like a car: when a car isn't running smoothly, you take it to the mechanic, they can diagnose what's mechanically wrong, and make adjustments or swap out parts to get that car back to smooth running.</p>
<p>But the body isn't a machine.</p>
<p>It's an ecosystem.</p>
<p>And chronically ill bodies are places where the ecosystem has been thrown out of whack, due to pollution or invasive species or catastrophic event or something else. We don't ever expect that these ecosystems will return to their original composition, but we do expect that they will find a new homeostasis.</p>
<hr>
<p>So that's how I'd been describing things, to the extent that I was describing them.</p>
<p>I just finished reading Cal Flyn's book <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/islands-of-abandonment-nature-rebounding-in-the-post-human-landscape-cal-flyn/15606084?ean=9781984878212" title="Islands of Abandonment" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Islands of Abandonment: Nature Rebounding in the Post-Human Landscape</a>.</p>
<p>In it, Flyn recounts stories and travel experiences to abandoned/damaged areas and how those areas rebound.</p>
<p>Metaphorically appropriate, no?</p>
<p>At any rate, there's a section in the book talking about ecosystems that have been ravaged by non-native species, what we most commonly call invasive species. I'm just going to quote directly here (p. 222):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That non-native species should be able to settle in--and even come to serve some helpful roles--does throw a little cold water over the idea of the ecosystem as the intricately wrought, carefully balanced product of millennia of coevolution, each species carving its way into the genes of the others' as water sculpts rocks. Indeed, it is the success of aliens like maesopsis, all over the world, that has fed into a bold new perspective, one that seeks to reevaluate environments "tainted" by the proliferation of non-native species.<br><br>Such ecosystems, suggests this new school of thought, are "novel ecosystems"--created by man, but self-sustaining. And it is time to accept the fact that they have changed forever, cannot be returned to a previous "unspoiled" state--indeed, that the notion of their being spoiled in the first place may be incorrect--and appreciate them, for what they are now. It is, write its proponents, "the new ecological world order." They quote Goethe: "[Nature] is ever shaping new forms: what is, has never yet been; what has been, comes not again."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I keep turning this over in my mind, how wedded we are to the idea of taint or destruction of a pristine former state. Where does that idea of pristine nature--or, for that matter, a "healthy" body as the natural default--come from? Are we wedded to the idea of the body as machine because that makes it less terrifying and unpredictable (as nature can be)?</p>
<hr>
<p>They're not easy questions to try to unravel, and truthfully today my brain is foggy enough, my energy low enough, that it's futile to ask.</p>
<p>But there's something here, in that idea of appreciating a novel ecosystem--that something is not spoiled, but merely different from what we expected, but no less complex and no less worthy of appreciation.</p>
<p>Imagine, for a moment, that an ecosystem has a consciousness. That it's conscious of itself as an entity. (Here, I tend to think of systems I know well--watersheds where I've hiked, areas I've lived. Maybe there's calming water or big sentinel trees or just a vista I know well--picture one that makes sense to you.)</p>
<p>Imagine what that consciousness experiences when a wildly invasive new species shows up, smothering all the patterns and balances that were there before, throwing everything off-kilter.</p>
<p>There'd be all the feelings of grief, I suspect. Rage, sadness, denial, depression...so many feelings.</p>
<p>But ecosystems don't just stop; they keep going. Eventually, that so-called invasive species usually hits a point where the ecosystem can't sustain its insane growth, and the invasive species population semi-collapses--or some other piece of the ecosystem adapts to limit it. From that point onward, that non-native species becomes a part of the ecosystem--sometimes, even, a very integral part of it.</p>
<p>True, there's a lot potentially lost here: native species that couldn't compete and have been obliterated, maybe entire segments of the ecosystem.</p>
<p>But I imagine the ecosystem would feel sort of proud, at that point. It might look back on the before times with a bit of sadness, but there would also be pride at having weathered that shit time when everything seemed to be falling apart. Pride at having survived that time, pride in achieving a newer version of itself that is now balanced again rather than giving up. The details won't ever be the same, the balance might be a bit more tenuous and fragile than before, but what an achievement.</p>
<p>It's not that hard for me to imagine, because quite honestly, this is my life.</p>
<p>I had an unusual, highly-invasive virus enter the ecosystem of my body, and it threw off a careful balance that had been working pretty darn well my whole life. And for the first couple years, that intruder threw my ecosystem into chaos. Nothing could be expected to work as it did before, even things that seemed like they should have been unaffected somehow were. It felt like there was no way forward.</p>
<p>Yet, somehow, slowly, some sense of balance has returned. It's nowhere near the balance I had before--it's definitely more fragile. Things work very differently than they did before, and as a consequence, my life and my self are very different. I keep having to try to re-embrace the idea of letting go of the previous version of this ecosystem. Looking at pictures of how strong and stable and well-constructed it once was just makes me long for those "unspoiled" days. (If they ever existed...increasingly, I think the perception of them as unspoiled was itself deeply flawed.)</p>
<p>But the fact that my ecosystem body has found any path forward--that I'm not still in the throes of the really dark days of 2020 and 2021, that I no longer feel like I'm slipping into dementia and going to run out of air, that my skin isn't erupting in weird hive-like responses to certain stimuli, I have any sense of taste or smell at all, and I don't wake up each day with a fresh hellacious symptom--it's really f*cking amazing, frankly.</p>
<p>Thanks to the novel coronavirus and the ways it impacted my body, I am now a novel ecosystem.</p>
<p>In a world where we're coming to grips with the omnipresence of microplastics, forever chemicals like PFAS, Superfund sites, kudzu, pythons, hitchhiking zebra mussels, and climate change, our entire world is becoming a patchwork of novel ecosystems.</p>
<p>Maybe this just puts me one step ahead of the game in understanding that and still finding a way to get out of bed each day.</p>
<p>Or maybe it just makes it easier for me to explain what this feels like.😅</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why breaking my Duolingo streak is an act of self-care</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/duolingo-streak-blue-blaze.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/duolingo-streak-blue-blaze.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/IMG_20180709_070625.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2023-01-02T12:35:02-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/IMG_20180709_070625.jpg" alt="An Appalachian Trail sign on a tree, marked with a blue blaze. The sign reads &quot;Bad Weather Trail&quot; with an arrow pointing to the left." />
                    This year, I'm starting off the new year with a somewhat unorthodox choice: to break my 1294-day Duolingo streak. I know that's the opposite of most people's New Year's resolutions, so it probably warrants a bit of explanation. I've been using Duolingo since July 2015.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/IMG_20180709_070625.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="An Appalachian Trail sign on a tree, marked with a blue blaze. The sign reads &quot;Bad Weather Trail&quot; with an arrow pointing to the left." /></p>
                <p>This year, I'm starting off the new year with a somewhat unorthodox choice: to break my 1294-day Duolingo streak.</p>
<p>I know that's the opposite of most people's New Year's resolutions, so it probably warrants a bit of explanation.</p>
<p>I've been using Duolingo since July 2015. For most of that time, I've maintained streaks of activity, though before 2019 I didn't really care about the streak. I'd been wanting to learn French for years. Duolingo was easy to fit into my day, even when I traveled a lot for work. And at least once I almost "finished" the French course, only to have a redesign and restructure kick me back down several levels.</p>
<p>I've had a few times where I got out of the habit. Thru-hiking the Appalachian Trail, for example: I didn't practice French at all then. And I was a bit patchy picking it back up after I finished the trail, until I started using a habit-tracking app that I set to ask me every day if I'd practiced Duolingo.</p>
<p>In early 2020, I was on a several-months' streak and enjoying the consistency of the habit.</p>
<p>Then, of course, I got sick with Covid and developed long Covid, with brain fog and fatigue. I already had a 200+ day streak at that point. And although I often could only make it through a review or a single lesson in a day, I clung stubbornly to this routine. I didn't drop my streak, despite being so full of fatigue I couldn't get out of bed and often forgetting English words I used all the time--French was much harder.</p>
<p>Long Covid took so much from me for so long. I went from being an endurance athlete to, almost overnight, getting winded going up a flight of stairs. My heart rate was all over the place; my steel trap memory suddenly had gaping holes where things used to be. For a while I couldn't even focus enough to read. Duolingo was, in a very real way, one of the only habits that I successfully carried over from the before long Covid (BLC) times.</p>
<p>I have stuck with it, working my way through every verb tense, learning a bunch of sentences that have no real meaning in real life. Just a couple weeks ago, I finally "finished" the French course (though, of course, thanks to more redesigns, I haven't actually finished unless I hit the Legendary level on all previous levels). I still wouldn't say I can speak French at all. My audio processing is pretty slow, and my speech isn't awesome. I can read it passably well. But I've developed a decent foundation.</p>
<p>So why, you might be asking, did I give up that 1294-day streak?</p>
<p>It's a multi-layered answer.</p>
<p>The first part is that I hate the new UI and format they rolled out a few weeks ago. I was one of those learners who focused singularly on a given skill and worked all the way through it before moving on (which was a boon with my brain fog, since it often took staggering levels of repetition before I could bludgeon my memory to make space for things). The new layout makes that impossible, and it's left me feeling constantly insecure and confused.</p>
<p>The second part is that I have achieved a chunk of the goal I set out for myself: I got all the way through the course, all levels (ignoring Legendary, which has only existed for a little while).</p>
<p>But the third part is...harder to articulate.</p>
<p>Why would I cut this one continuous thread of my BLC brain and life?</p>
<p>For me, Duolingo was about setting an intention in my life (to rudimentarily learn French) and sticking to that intention. For a long time, that intention made me feel good. I did Duolingo every day (usually in the morning, sometimes at night). I learned things. It was fun.</p>
<p>Even once I got into some of the trickier verb tenses that were pretty hard to "intuitively" wrap my head around and it felt more like work, it still felt good. My stressed and stretched-thin long Covid brain could still do this thing I used to be able to do. That felt important. It was an act of resistance against this poorly-defined, poorly-understood, untreatable illness.</p>
<p>But here, starting 2023, coming up quite quickly on my 3rd year anniversary of having long Covid, I find that I want to let go of some of those threads to BLC me.</p>
<p>There's a lot of grief with chronic illness. Lots of grief and lots of mourning. We lose so much: a sense of stability and predictability, the unexamined presumption of "health" as "normal", all the identities we once had that our bodies make unsustainable. The self basically disintegrates before our eyes and we are left trying to find some way to move forward. Some way to have hope when all of the specific things you once hoped for are no longer possible with the increasingly finite, wildly unpredictable resources your body allows.</p>
<p>I've been reading Arthur W. Frank's <em>The Wounded Storyteller</em>. Frank identifies a few common narrative models that people with serious illness can follow: restitution, chaos, and quest. And I can see that evolution in my own thinking. I held onto Duolingo for a while because I assumed I'd recover and I didn't want to have lost my streak (restitution). Then I held onto it because everything in my life and my very self was dissolving, crumbling, and was so unpredictable I couldn't find words to describe it (chaos). It was a tiny moment of consistency in an otherwise tumultuous storm.</p>
<p>But now, starting this year, I'm thinking a lot more about intentionality as it relates to long Covid. In discussing the importance of testimony and recognition with chronic illness, Frank says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The danger for ill people is that they are often taught how to be ill by professionals. Illness is not presented to the ill as a moral problem; people are not asked, after the shock of diagnosis has dulled sufficiently, what do you wish to <strong>become</strong> in this experience? What story do you wish to tell of yourself? How will you shape your illness, and yourself, in the stories you tell of it? (159)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I can't fully answer these questions yet, though my posts here are one way I'm trying to find my way to those answers.</p>
<p>What I do know is that I don't want to be clinging to some sense of what used to be normal. Even in the vague way that Duolingo has provided, there is always this subtle feeling of difference between how that experience is<em> now</em> vs. what it was like <em>before</em>.</p>
<p>I don't want my story to be: here's this thing I used to do really easily and now I'm tenaciously sticking to it even though it's really hard and isn't fun or rewarding at all. That's empty stubbornness, and almost willful clinging to the past.</p>
<p>Long Covid has taught me how expressly important it is, as a chronically ill person, to be adaptable. To define--and redefine--for yourself what a full life looks like. Because you're the only one who can. You're the only one who understands what feels like a reasonable challenge vs. an unachievable and almost cruel challenge.</p>
<p>So I would like to redefine this. I'm walking away from Duolingo, but not learning French. My plan is to start trying to read more actual things in French, try to listen to some of the easy French podcasts, and seek out other alternatives that aren't as tidy as an app that tracks my completion but that can give me back some of those feelings of fulfillment and competence I had before. Free from the tyranny of the streak, my hope is that I can structure and pursue learning as it makes sense in my life.</p>
<p>Resolutions are often about habits. They're about expressing an intention and then committing action to follow through on that intention.</p>
<p>So my resolution is to let go of this highly structured but no longer purposeful habit and explore alternative habits that help me pick up the melody of the original goal but in a tune that my current body can carry.</p>
<p>On the Appalachian Trail, there are a lot of places where you can choose to follow side trails--which are often more scenic and are sometimes shorter. The AT is marked with white blazes; the side trails are generally blue. On my thru-hike, I was a religious white blaze follower. It's taken me an extra 4+ years, nerve damage in my feet, and a chronic untreatable illness, but I think I'm finally coming around to the idea of blue-blazing. Because sometimes how you choose to make your way is even more important than the journey itself.</p>
<p>And if my story here can be useful in any way, I hope that's what you take from it: you always can--and should--walk away from things that aren't serving you or are causing undue stress. You don't have to wield self-control like a mace. Offer your body and your mind a little grace and see what makes your life feel whole rather than full.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/IMG_20180513_082713.jpg" alt="Appalachian Trail sign. The sign reads &quot;Mau-Har Trail. Maupin Field Shelter 3.0&quot; with an arrow to the left. In marker, people have written several statements: &quot;Cheaters shortcut&quot;, &quot;Voldemort was a purist&quot;, and &quot;Take the blue blaze!&quot;" width="4048" height="3036" sizes="100vw" srcset="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-xs.jpg 300w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-sm.jpg 480w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-md.jpg 768w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-lg.jpg 1024w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-xl.jpg 1360w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/6/responsive/IMG_20180513_082713-2xl.jpg 1600w">
<figcaption >Take the blue blaze!</figcaption>
</figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Third time&#x27;s the charm: Sass loses taste and smell yet again</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/third-times-the-charm.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/third-times-the-charm.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/5/PXL_20221119_203614849.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2022-12-16T17:27:58-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/5/PXL_20221119_203614849.jpg" alt="Photo of a cove on the coast of Maine. The sun is setting and the tide is out, revealing lots of dried brown grass and plants." />
                    Earlier this week, my partner made a vegetarian curry dish with sweet potatoes, chickpeas, and rice. Three bites into the meal, I realized I couldn't taste the curry. At all. Since then, I've been paying attention and I'm back to where I was about a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/5/PXL_20221119_203614849.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Photo of a cove on the coast of Maine. The sun is setting and the tide is out, revealing lots of dried brown grass and plants." /></p>
                <p>Earlier this week, my partner made a vegetarian curry dish with sweet potatoes, chickpeas, and rice.</p>
<p>Three bites into the meal, I realized I couldn't taste the curry. At all.</p>
<p>Since then, I've been paying attention and I'm back to where I was about a year ago, with limited sense of taste and reduced sense of smell.</p>
<p>When I mention this to most overall healthy people, they immediately ask me what I think caused it. Sometimes I answer this question by running through a list of vaguely logical options:</p>
<ul>
<li>About 4 weeks ago, I completed a 5k doing 60-second run-walk intervals. It was cold and my body hated it, my heart rate was higher than it had been for my training. The cold stressed my body and I almost puked by the end of the race. Maybe this had long-term repercussions.</li>
<li>About 2 weeks ago, I got a flu shot. I was quite sick the day after, mildly okay two days after, and then quite sick again the day after that. I've been tired since then, back to the land of "can't get enough sleep". Maybe the flu shot was a bad idea (did it trigger a disproportionate inflammatory response in my immune system?). Or getting it "so soon" after the 5k was too much. Or maybe it's nothing.</li>
<li>It's actually winter now. My body seems to hate the cold, so it could just be the fact of winter itself causing issues, somehow.</li>
<li>It's actually winter now, so our forced air furnace is running. My body doesn't seem to like the HVAC system in our rental, so maybe that's triggering it. Or, in tandem with the cold. Or, in tandem with any of the other bullet points listed above.</li>
</ul>
<p>But what I really want to say to them is: I have a long Covid body. 1 + 1 stopped adding up to 2 in my body 2.5+ years ago. There doesn't have to be a reason. Sometimes you just hit a point of stress that causes a flare of symptoms, and it's hard to say exactly what it is.</p>
<p>All I can do at this point is to try to remove stressors, get lots of rest, and hope.</p>
<p>Though there are things I don't tell them.</p>
<p>I don't tell them that the night I ate that curry, I went into the bathroom to take my shower and sobbed through my whole shower.</p>
<p>Because you think you've found a way to manage your illness, you think it kind of makes sense and now you can make things livable. And then something that you worked really hard to regain disappears again, just like that, and you're reminded not only that none of it is within your control, not only that the doctors still can't do diddly squat to help you, but also that every time you lose it, you're going to be full of grief. There is no "normal", anymore. There's a baseline that you try to maintain and some days are great and some are still really shitty. And you're not really sure how you managed to get good days for a while once the bad ones return.</p>
<p>I also don't tell them that when I voiced fear about the 5k or the flu shot tipping my body over the edge, they told me I shouldn't live my life in fear and to just do it. What I want to scream at them is that this isn't irrational fear: given the data I have to work with, it is completely legitimate, warranted fear. The idea that I might have somehow brought this on myself by these "risky" actions--actions which most everyone else didn't consider risky at all--is so sour I want to spit it out of my mouth. (Or it would be, if I could taste sour things.)</p>
<p>I cried, but I also wanted to scream. I wanted to rage around the house and break things, and just...lash out with all of it. I didn't. I sobbed in the shower and went to bed. Then I managed to tell my whole team at work that I'm sicker again and will need some grace and flexibility; please don't schedule back-to-back meetings with me for hours on end. And I started testing what I can and can't taste and smell. The losses aren't as bad as 2020 and 2021's were, I still have a few flavors I can taste that aren't salt or hot sauce, and a few smells that aren't burning things and dog farts (which were the two smells I could smell for all of 2020 and a good chunk of 2021).</p>
<p>But if there's all this stuff I won't say to most people, why write about it here?</p>
<p>Well, the first reason is simple: I need to speak this out so it doesn't just fester in my body and turn me bitter and rageful. Venting some steam.</p>
<p>But also: somewhere out there, I imagine there's another spoonie who's also going through a recurring loss of a good baseline. And that loss slapped them in the face, took their breath away, and left them sobbing and confused and lonely and angry and sad all at once. Whatever that loss was, it probably seemed small to outsiders (aren't you used to this by now?) and yet it feels huge and overwhelming and how on earth does any of us go on living.</p>
<p>So you, random chronically ill person I don't actually know: I'm writing this for you. You're not alone. That rage and grief and confusion you're feeling? It's totally normal for your situation. There are lots of us who go through the same things. I'm here to write a little of it down so that we can both recognize that the emperor has no f*cking clothes on and maybe laugh or cry a bit about how absurd it is that no one else notices.</p>
<p>Also, if your sense of taste and smell still work, please go eat some curry and revel in what an amazing thing those senses are. Lean your face over the bowl or plate, close your eyes, and inhale deeply and just f*cking luxuriate in it. Take a couple bites and let them sit in your mouth a little longer so you can get the full wave of different flavors. And then send me a single thought of flare recovery vibes. 🙃</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On resiliency: Why I ditched the &quot;you&#x27;ll get better&quot; narrative</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/on-resiliency.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/on-resiliency.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/IMG_20180517_111208.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2022-04-01T12:50:08-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/IMG_20180517_111208.jpg" alt="A rocky overlook shrouded in fog" />
                    As I've thought about Hike the Hike You've Been Given, and what that has looked like in my thru-hiking and long Covid life, I've realized that I can probably distill it down even further. Accepting the hike or chronic illness or whatever it is you've been&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/IMG_20180517_111208.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A rocky overlook shrouded in fog" /></p>
                <p>As I've thought about <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/hike-the-hike-youve-been-given.html" title="Hike the Hike You've Been Given" target="null">Hike the Hike You've Been Given</a>, and what that has looked like in my thru-hiking and long Covid life, I've realized that I can probably distill it down even further. </p>
<p>Accepting the hike or chronic illness or whatever it is you've been given is also about reclaiming the story of your life. It's taking a story that has some seriously negative turns to it and viewing it in a positive way.</p>
<p>I'm not talking about forced or toxic positivity. This isn't let's pretend it's all sunshine and roses.</p>
<p>It is, instead, to focus on a core thread in the story itself.</p>
<p>For me, that thread is resiliency.</p>
<p>I have to thank Amy, the long Covid therapist I saw, for this word. It has a lot of power. 🙌</p>
<p class="dropcap">One of the things I've found hardest about having long Covid is that a lot of very well-intentioned, well-meaning people spent weeks and months telling me that I'd "get back to where I was before in no time." We've probably all said something like this to a friend going through a break-up, a job change, or other tough times, and it's meant as a reassurance, a way of saying: hey, I know it sucks right now, but this is abnormal and you'll get back to normal soon enough. Chin up.</p>
<p>But there are times that this is the complete opposite of reassuring.</p>
<p>First of all, it assumes that the "normal" state of life for most of us is one of stability and a fixed, defined identity. That's patently false.</p>
<p>"Normal" life is a rollercoaster. Things are always falling apart and coming back together, then falling apart again. Stuff breaks. We get stressed, we get anxious, we get depressed.</p>
<p>Trying to define "normal" as somehow absent of those things has this implicit effect of making us feel bad for not being "normal". And if your situation is turning out to be more chronic and long-lasting--like long Covid, for example--it makes you feel like you will never be "normal" again. No bueno.</p>
<p>Thru-hikers often intuitively pick up on this. The trail gives you endless ups and downs, every day. You might score a beautiful camping spot only to have it downpour for the next four days, and you're putting on still soaking wet socks and shirt. You might push hard to get to a summit that's supposed to have gorgeous views just to have it walled in with fog. You might get an amazing care package full of love and good food from friends but it weighs more than the rest of your pack combined. Or the trail you're supposed to be hiking might look like this:</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/IMG_20180623_102309-2.jpg" alt="A steep uphill sloped covered in a jumble of rocks. In the distance at the top of the hill, a tree with AT white trail blazes indicates the rock jumble IS the trail." width="3036" height="4048" sizes="100vw" srcset="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-xs.jpg 300w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-sm.jpg 480w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-md.jpg 768w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/3/responsive/IMG_20180623_102309-2-2xl.jpg 1600w">
<figcaption >No, this is not a random jumble of rocks. See the trail blaze at the very top? It's the trail. :)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p class="dropcap">But more than this false measure of "normal", the entire piece of advice strips you of the story of overcoming difficulties. Of being resilient.</p>
<p>When friends or family told me I'd get back to normal before I knew it, or back to where I'd been health- or fitness-wise, my response changed over time.</p>
<p>In the first few days and weeks, it was a kind of reassurance. This was temporary, and the reassurance felt good.</p>
<p>But as this dragged on to months and then years, it seemed flat and full of denial.</p>
<p>And eventually, it felt gross to me because the fact was: I'd been through a lot of shit <em>and I wanted to celebrate that, own it, and have people recognize it.</em></p>
<p>Let's be real: it's really shitty to have long Covid. It's weeks and months of riding a rollercoaster of exhaustion and fatigue, where it takes every ounce of will-power you might have just to get out of bed and do even simple things. The brain fog can be mild (taking a split-second longer to remember a thing) or thick and heavy (forgetting names of people, forgetting major emotional events just days after they happen).</p>
<p>I still have very little sense of smell or taste two years in. I've had random allergic skin reactions to a range of foods I used to eat regularly. I have persistent tinnitus in one ear and hypersensitive hearing the rest of the time. Each day is like a roulette wheel of symptoms, and though my daily baseline has improved with time, it's still a roulette wheel. The consequences are just a bit more expected and predictable now than they were in 2020.</p>
<p>When you tell me I'll be back where I was, you basically erase all of that struggle because you don't acknowledge it. You sweep it under the rug as a "temporary" thing. I'm two years in. This isn't temporary. This is my new normal. And it's a really hard normal.</p>
<p class="dropcap">Quite frankly: it's the biggest endurance effort I've ever undertaken. Way harder than thru-hiking, which I could choose to quit at any time. I don't get to opt out of this reality. There are no zero days, no trail magic, no quitting and going home. Like Groundhog Day, I wake up to this same reality no matter what I do.</p>
<p>I'm not saying all of that so that you'll have sympathy or pity for me.</p>
<p>I'm saying it because: I'm resilient. I continue to live in this shifting roulette, and I do it reasonably gracefully. Most people have no idea how rough my day to day life is. I'm still working, still walking my dog, still cooking even if I can't properly taste what I make. I have some dreams and some hopes now, too, which was unthinkable a year ago.</p>
<p>I'm a resilient warrior. I've been through so much, and continue to go through so much.</p>
<p>So don't tell me I'll get back to being who I used to be. That woman is long gone. The woman I am now is much wiser even if her brain doesn't work as well. She's gentler, more thoughtful, generally a better listener. She thinks more from her heart than her head. She considers that people bring all kinds of baggage to each interaction that might not be remotely visible.</p>
<p>She's a kinder person, even if she has way less energy.</p>
<p>And I want you to see her and know that She. Is. Me. Not that picture you have of me from 2.5 years ago. Messy, exhausted, fatigued me, now. And I'll continue to grow and change as I keep living with this condition. I'll keep being in turns angry and disappointed in medical science for not being able to help me, and I'll keep trying to figure out ways to help myself.</p>
<p class="dropcap">In so many ways, all of us--every single damn one of us--need to drop this story of stability being "normal" and this other stuff being a detour or a distraction. It's neither. Life is always this mixture of more stable and less stable things, of pleasure and pain, of mountain summits and grueling rough terrain. If there's one thing I wish I could tell my pre-long-Covid self, it's that: stop thinking it's supposed to be great all the time and you're somehow messing up if it's not. It's supposed to be a grab bag, and the people who are living with sass are rolling with whatever comes out of that bag, every day.</p>
<p>Don't try to get back to some previously stable/amazing point in your life--recognize that you're a more amazing person now having gone through all that stuff and continuing to go through and still getting up and living your life anyway.</p>
<p>Find your resilient story. I promise you, it's in there. You've overcome a lot, and you'll overcoming a lot, and THAT is the story of your life. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/about.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/about.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/2/IMG_20180428_082144_1.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-10-20T15:53:10-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/2/IMG_20180428_082144_1.jpg" alt="" />
                    Hi, I'm Kate, also known as Sassafras. In 2018, I hiked the Appalachian Trail, solo. I developed serious nerve problems in my feet but still completed my hike. In March of 2020, I contracted COVID. I soon developed what's called longhaul Covid or just Long&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/2/IMG_20180428_082144_1.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Hi, I'm Kate, also known as Sassafras.</p>
<p>In 2018, I hiked the Appalachian Trail, solo. I developed serious nerve problems in my feet but still completed my hike.</p>
<p>In March of 2020, I contracted COVID. I soon developed what's called longhaul Covid or just Long Covid (I may abbreviate this as LC, too).</p>
<p>This site is my attempt to make sense of all those experiences and draw parallels between them, to share talks or other presentations I've given, and just generally to offer support to others facing challenging endurance efforts and chronic illnesses.</p>
<p>I believe we can all live our lives with a little more sass.</p>
<p>See <a href="http://www.livewithsass.com/tags/presentationswithsass/" title="Presentations with sass">Presentations with sass</a> for recordings of talks I've given.</p>
<p>And if you're interested in having me give a talk in-person or virtually at your event or organization, <a href="mailto:hikingwithsass@gmail.com" title="contact me" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">please reach out</a>!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hike the Hike You&#x27;ve Been Given</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate / Sassafras</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.livewithsass.com/hike-the-hike-youve-been-given.html"/>
        <id>http://www.livewithsass.com/hike-the-hike-youve-been-given.html</id>
        <media:content url="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/1/IMG_20180508_170133.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="longhaulerwithsass"/>
            <category term="hikerwithsass"/>

        <updated>2022-12-16T17:28:37-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/1/IMG_20180508_170133.jpg" alt="A red eft crouches on some gravel and sticks" />
                    Before I began my hike, I had an image of what it would be like. Of course, I knew there would be rain and mud and miserable days, that my body would hurt, that my pack would feel too heavy. I imagined getting sick of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="http://www.livewithsass.com/media/posts/1/IMG_20180508_170133.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="A red eft crouches on some gravel and sticks" /></p>
                <div>Before I began my hike, I had an image of what it would be like. Of course, I knew there would be rain and mud and miserable days, that my body would hurt, that my pack would feel too heavy. I imagined getting sick of foods, the grossness of unwashed clothing and my body. But underneath all of that, I thought my body would be basically fine: maybe some blisters, some bruises, some weight loss, but fundamentally fine.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I'd been hiking for years, distance cycling and triathlon training 6 days a week for nearly a year. I'd managed Achilles and knee issues. I figured my triathlete body would kind of love "only" having to hike, and that I'd be pulling 20 or 30-mile days with no problem. I expected it to take me somewhere between 3-5 months, though I budgeted for longer just in case.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The reality quickly became quite different. The nerve problems in my feet began at Fontana Dam, less than 200 miles into the nearly 2200-mile trail. My feet felt like they were being stabbed, or burned, or like I was walking on glass. With every step.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Suddenly, my body, which had always submitted to nearly everything I'd pushed it to do with fairly minimal complaint (minus my overuse injuries), became foreign to me. I tried so many different solutions and treatments for my feet. I frequently cried on trail, in frustration, in pain. My miles slowed. I had to take far more frequent breaks than most of the people hiking around me, sometimes more than the retired guys I hiked with. I certainly wasn't keeping up with the 20-somethings.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I knew, deep inside, that the only way to solve my foot problems was to quit.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I also knew that if I quit, it would gnaw at me and I'd eventually find myself back out here, except with full knowledge of how awful it would be to my body, and having to save and plan and quit my job and put my things in storage all over again.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>My feet screamed at me every morning, every night, every time I took a break, every time I got up from taking a break, literally every step: stop. Stop. Stop.Though I considered the idea, I couldn't. I wished I could. (To this day, in some ways, part of me wishes I could have quit and saved my feet. But I am stubborn to a fault.)</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The traits I'd always had, which endurance sport training had further helped solidify, suddenly became foundational pillars of my day to day: endure. Adapt.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But there was still so much pain, and I felt bitterness and resentment at my fellow hikers who had comparatively simple problems to manage--blisters, occasional injuries from falls, but nothing lingering.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The hikers with feet like mine quit. That's what they did.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>In Virginia, as I stopped hiking or even camping with any of my tramily, I started to descend to really dark places. It was so unfair. This wasn't the hike I'd signed up for. This sucked.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Two events changed my perspective. I can't remember the order, I will have to check my journals, but:</div>
<ol>
<li>I met Repeat and Three-Mile. Three-Mile, on his second attempt, trying to manage his fibromyalgia, already having had to take a break to see his doctors. I really only saw them a couple days, and we camped together one night (I shared my Sourpatch Kids with them). I asked him how he managed thru-hiking with fibromyalgia, how on earth he made that work. And we got into this conversation about the importance of the mind, and perspective. As he put it to me: "It's like you're driving a bus. Your feet stepping on the ground are going on the gas and the brake, your hands on your hiking poles are like they're the steering wheel. You can't control what comes down the road at you, but you know what you can control? What you allow ON your bus." It was one of the more concrete explanations of deliberate focus and mindfulness I'd ever heard, and it came at a time when I desperately needed that perspective.</li>
<li>My dad met me in Shenandoah National Park. We ate meals together, gave my friends trail magic, shared two different hotel rooms, drove portions of the scenic drive. I talked about my feet, how hard it was. He watched me get out of bed and almost fall over, have to use walls to help me stand up and balance until my feet "woke up" for the day. The last morning as we ate breakfast before parting ways, he looked at me over the table and said: "I wish you were having more fun." It was like someone had punched me in the stomach. I wanted to cry. Instead, Dad dropped me back on trail, on a foggy, rainy day in the Shenandoahs when you couldn't see any of the beautiful views. And I started sobbing and talking to my dead mother as I went.</li>
</ol>
<div> </div>
<div>I knew that I had lost my joy and enthusiasm. That I had let the pain and the struggle dominate my thoughts, and the more of my time and effort I put focusing on them, the larger they loomed.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I worked to refocus myself to things that kept me more in the moment: photographing mushrooms (one of my day-hiking hobbies), saying "Hi, little red eft" to every red eft I saw on trail, shifting to as much solo stealth camping as I could to pick beautiful places to eat dinner and sleep.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>As I did this, I realized that what I had to let go of was the hike I thought I'd have. I had to embrace and hike the hike that I'd been given, instead. I never did a 30-mile day, never pulled the massive individual daily endurance efforts I imagined. I took frequent breaks, my pace was slower, I camped in weird places and soaked my feet in a lot of very cold water crossings. It forced me out of my body, in many ways. And when it was negative, I spent a lot of time in my head, in very neurotic places there. But as I consciously shifted my focus to the present and to accepting the hike I'd been given, this shifted me more into my heart, to remind myself how grateful I was for this opportunity.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>From then on, the worse my feet got (and they got quite bad), I told myself when I got up that I needed to treat the day as if it were my last day on trail. How would I want to spend my last day on trail? Miserable? Or joyful? That constant reminder of just how fragile and tenuous my hike was forced a different attitude and appreciation.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>In the end, my hike was much richer for it. I have watched snakes swim across Maine ponds, hung in my hammock with no human anywhere nearby through thunderstorms, watched the moon from my hammock. If I'd been pulling huge miles and taking fewer breaks, I don't know that I would have done as many of these things, or noticed them as much when I did, as I soaked my feet.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>My hike took 5.5 months.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>And there isn't a day now that I don't wish I wasn't back out there.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Fast-forward 3 years, to 2021. It's about a month after the three-year trailiversary of finishing my thru-hike. I've had long Covid since I got sick with it in the end of March 2020. My body, once an endurance machine, is a constant roulette game: some days I feel okay, some days I have shortness of breath from having a conversation, often I'm totally exhausted. I haven't had a real workout in over a year, since they seemed to cause flares of the worst issues.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>In short, this life is not the life I expected to have.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I can't say that I've been able to fully accept the life that long Covid has given me, yet. No one knows if this will last forever, if I might "get better," and that uncertainty makes it rocky. Some days I am full of rage or sadness or depression or bleakness. Some days I do inch my way toward acceptance.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The red efts are harder to find, basically nonexistent where I live. But I have a daily short hike with my dog Zola, and we look for mushrooms, and her sheer joy at being out on trail is infectious. This isn't the life or the hike that I expected or wanted. No one would choose this. But I am doing my best to live it to the fullest extent I can, within the ever-shifting parameters of my now chronically ill body.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>On the rough days, sometimes, I mutter to myself: "Hike the hike you've been given, Sass." And I try to remember who Sassafras was, what she accomplished, and to remind myself that no matter what my body does, *I am still that hiker with sass*. No virus can take away that experience, that mindset, that tremendous accomplishment, that fortitude. I may be stuck on an endless endurance effort with no Katahdin ever in sight--and a dwindling sense that there will ever be a Katahdin, here--but I can still try to face each day as if it's my last on this adventure.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Hi, little red eft.</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
